hi and welcome to my channel living in
Central Texas I'm Andrea dudic associate
broker and realtor with vist real
estate so you're curious about the
difference between a general home
inspection and a VA inspection also
known as a VA appraisal well stay tuned
I'm going to cover it all your home
inspection is going to look a little bit
different depending on the type of home
that you're purchasing you can purchase
a new construction home never lived in
or you can purchase a resale home which
has been previously owned
now with a new construction home
typically you're going to have
warranties associated with that new
build including a one-year General
Builder warranty which is basically a
bumper-to-bumper warranty 2-year major
systems which is your HVAC electrical
and plumbing and a 10-year Foundation
warranty those might vary slightly but
those are pretty standard for this area
even if you have a new construction home
I would say half of my buyers obtain 30
party inspections and half of them don't
because really yes you do have most
things covered in that first year
especially um sometimes it's just really
nice to have a third-party inspector
come to the home check out everything
and then we're able to just hand that
full report over to the Builder go over
it with them and cover everything you
know that everything's good before you
move in versus moving in and maybe
things coming up and having to file
warranty claims again not necessary but
still helpful now with a resale home
that's going to look a little bit
different here in Texas we have what we
call an option period once you go under
contract on a home once everyone is
agreed and the contract is fully
executed we're going to have that option
period that has been negotiated which is
you as the buyer your unrestricted right
to terminate the contract for whatever
reason what we typically do in that time
frame though is encourage you to get a
home inspection and then we try and
negotiate major repairs um those are
usually big expense or safety related
items or the things that we typically
see in there so if your third party home
inspector comes out they're going to get
on the roof check your roof maybe spin a
laser level check the foundation look at
all of your electrical systems turn on
all the plumbing throughout the house
check every door knob is the toilet
loose I mean everything that you can
imagine because they're going to tell
you exactly what you're purchasing with
this home now what I usually like to say
is we don't hand over the full report
and say hey Mr seller fixed everything
in this report because it's not a brand
new home but we do want to make sure
that we're addressing again those safety
items or things that are going to cost
you a lot of money at that time we do
all negotiations in your option period
because that's your negotiation window
the buyer can terminate during that time
period but the seller cannot so we want
to do all of our negotiations for for
you and try to get you the very best
outcome in moving forward with this home
if negotiations are made the seller
could say we'll fix items one and two
but we're not going to fix number three
or we'll fix items one and two and we'll
give you x amount off the purchase price
or x amount towards your closing cost
additional now when I negotiate repairs
for my clients I always put things like
all repairs to be completed by licensed
technician
uh receipts to be provided for all
documentation is everything a VA
appraisal AKA a VA inspection is going
to look very different so after a VA
buyer goes under contract they're still
going to have that same um option period
to which they can get a third party
inspection and make their
negotiations after that option period
has passed the lender is going to send
out an appraiser to make sure two things
one that the home really is worth what
it is under contract for because A
lender is not going to lend more money
than a house is worth so the appraiser
is going to come out look at the home
look at comparable properties look at
various things which I can go over in
another video but they want to make sure
that it meets value before they lend
money and they're also going to address
um any safety related items and make
sure that the home is livable they do
not do a a full inspection of the
property the same way a third-party
inspector would the other part to this
is a VA appraiser will call out certain
items that might be lender required
repairs again you're not getting that
full report back you're not getting a
full report and any negotiations that
could be done that's already passed if
it's not a lender required repair if it
is a lender required repair um the
seller is technically not required to do
that but typically they will to keep the
deal moving but that can lead into a
whole another sort of things definitely
recommended that you get that third
party inspection now I have had one
circumstance recently where a VA buyer
refused to have a third-party inspection
after they moved into the property
Unfortunately they discovered some very
horrible leaks and mold within the home
which had they elected to do a third
party inspection um that might have been
caught and that might have been
something that we could negotiate it was
something that the VA inspector
appraiser just didn't catch and then at
that point really fell on homeowners
insurance and home warranties that the
buyer had purchased otherwise all in all
a VA inspection and a thirdparty home
inspection are very different but
they're often confused and a lot of
times VA buyers think well I don't want
to pay for a third party inspection
because I'm already doing a VA
inspection and they're just not the same
and you really want to spend that money
to invest in your home and and um put
yourself an at an advantage in
negotiating things that might come up if
you have any questions about uh the home
buying process VA inspections third
party inspections you know where to find
me all my contact information is below
now if you're new to the channel don't
forget to subscribe to stay up toate on
all things real estate happening in
Central Texas like this video leave a
comment I'm here if you need anything
talk soon